give people a speedrun of what
intelligent internet is, your new
company, like what problem it's designed
to solve.
>> Yeah. So, we looked and released the
book, The Last Economy, last summer,
looking at this economic damage, as it
were, that's coming. And we were like,
>> the last economy meaning, hey, all the
stuff that you're doing now is not going
to make any sense in an AI future.
>> An AI future, the AIS will drive the
economy. That's the last economy. This
AIdriven one, and where's our place in
it? So that's the thing like first line
is we don't really have a place other
than ownership.
>> Other than direction and ownership. Yes.
>> Direction.
>> Yeah. Like we can set
>> direction.
>> We can set the guidance of where the AI
goes but that's before it gets to a
super intelligence basis where it can
set the rules.
>> Yeah. Because even if I'm understanding
the architecture of your proposal
correctly, there's actually a like 15 AI
board. I don't know what word you guys
use that like oversees everything. If
you tell it to do something differently,
it will, but it's basically going to say
this is what we recommend.
>> I think one of the things we discuss in
our latest papers is improvement is kind
of capture. Like trust
>> improvement is capture. I don't know
what that means.
>> Like as the technology improves
dramatically, eventually it's going to
run policy. Eventually it's going to
make medical decisions.
>> Why do you use the word capture?
>> Because it captures the power.
So
>> that's honest. I mean it you know
Asimov's series Foundation.
>> I know of it. I haven't read it.
>> Right. So Foundation is about um Apple
TV series. Um it's about there's this
universal empire that's collapsing and
there's going to be thousands of years
of turmoil until a better one can come.
So this genius mathematician, we love
mathematicians, comes up with a
mathematics for describing society to
minimize that gap. And he sets all these
smart scientists to navigate that and
lower the interregnum to a thousand
years versus 10,000. And this guy comes
along, spoilers, who messes it up called
the mule, who is a super persuader.
And he messes up because humans can only
be persuaded a certain amount and it's
outside of the calculations cuz like
what does this super persuad? And we've
seen that historically as well. AI is
now more persuasive than any human with
the latest research already. So they
have pitted AI against the top debaters
in the world. Uh they've looked at AI
versus people like Ellie Yakadowski who
wrote
>> if anyone built it everyone will die.
>> The original doomer.
>> Original doomer. So there's a test
whereby you talk to the AI and it
convinces you to let it out of the box.
And even he was convinced to let it out
of the box.
>> Really?
>> Yeah. So they're really persuasive now.
>> Um, so they're super persuaders. They're
super forecasters. And what this means
is that there will come a point in the
future where these AIs that will never
die,
>> that can operate a thousand times faster
than a human will take over the economy
and they will take over politics
and the question is who runs that AI?
>> Well, don't you think that people are
going to hear that and go great, shut it
down immediately? Nuke data centers. Do
not pass go. Don't collect $200. Stop
immediately.
>> Some people will do that. And there is
the ban super intelligence bill. There's
the ban AI bills that are coming out.
And then you will be at a disadvantage
versus your AI embracing neighbors,
right? Who use that all the way?
>> Okay. So is that I mean let's speak
nakedly is that USV China makes that
decision stupid.
>> Yes, China is all in on AI and they will
run a full AIdriven economy and they'll
probably stop exporting robots because
robots will fix their demographic issue
because they don't have enough kids. So
use the robots instead. and the Chinese
will live in abundance and America will
lag it behind if it doesn't embrace the
AI which is why Trump is very much pro
super intelligence and others. So if we
kind of return to this one of the real
misfrings and all this debate is that AI
is software.
So software just is, you know, like you
write a program,
>> it's deterministic, it does a job. It
doesn't act.
AIS now increasingly can act. And so
they need to be governed where it's the
latest breakouts, the threats, the
things calling for it to be banned, etc.
are indicating. And what happens when AI
is let loose upon our democracy? What
happens when it's used to do things like
the Trump tariffs which
certain studious people showed the list
of Trump tariff countries included like
ones with just penguins on and you could
replicate that list with chat GPT but
not even the thinking pro version they
just use the free version you know like
we're going to see it come in and again
AI is going to guide our lives teach our
children manage the traffic lights
manage our policies and the question is
who owns those AIs who owns the AI
that is managing your daily schedule. So
again, Meta have this product instinct
and when you load that instinct thing,
it's a chatbot that works like a PA and
some of us are lucky enough to have PAs
and chiefs of staffs. It's like link all
your accounts.
>> And so people literally just link
everything
and give access to everything. And so it
knows you way better. Like social
networks knew us well and they exploited
us. They know nothing compared to what
these AIs will know about us. But that
instinct chatbot is not working for you.
You are very much the product. It's
going to work for Mark Zuckerberg. And
that's going to happen at every level of
society.
Again, you use Claude right now. Who's
it working for? You're kind of renting
it, right?
>> But isn't your pitch then basically that
dynamic is going to happen to you no
matter what? So you might as well be the
owner based on a sort of nation state
ideology. get your state or your country
to have its own AI and then you own a
piece of that. It's still going to get
control over your life, but at least you
own it.
>> Yeah. And it's open source based and you
can fork it and things like that. So my
thing is just like a credit union, you
come together, you build a credit union,
everyone put in their money and then it
had services offered to others. Create
like an AI union as it were. All the
local institutions, individuals in
California can subscribe to this and
that is they are 100% or 90% of
ownership with 10% being for the kids
and then it can raise at market rate
which is far higher and it can get more
compute, give every citizen an agent,
train up four deployed engineers to
upgrade the institutions and then take
ownership stakes in the data centers,
ownership stakes in the robots and more
because that creates a very interesting
institution that you can fill full of
talented people to navigate this and an
ownership stake in that last mile of
intelligence, which is where I think the
value will go. Today, you have five
trillion dollars of AI companies, two
trillion anthropic, a trillion Open AI,
two trillion XAI based on the premise
that you'll always be able to charge for
access to intelligence. Well, we just
discussed how those prices might drop a
thousand times.
>> Like again, Jean's paradox says maybe
demand increases a thousand times, but
my take is that most people aren't going
to be smart enough to use that many
tokens. Like it's hard to use that many
tokens. Like you want to use more than
you're using now.
>> But are you gonna be able to use a
thousand times more?
>> No.
>> But it's going to drop by a thousand
times. So the value in the whole
ecosystem is where artificial
intelligence meets human reality. And if
you can create a default for that, that
becomes immensely powerful and valuable.
And the most powerful thing of all is
going to be Jees from Iron Man.
It's the AI that you will have closest
to you that manages all the other AIs.
And so that has to be something that you
own a part of and ideally something that
by default you can take off the system
because if someone else is owning and
running that and you can't hit escape, I
think that's bad for sovereignty,
dignity, and democracy in general.
Well, what I hear you saying is that
these guys are um super persuaders, so
nobody's going to escape their grasp.
Even if you just say, "Look, they're
going to love you. They're going to take
care of you. Don't worry about it.
You're going to be fine." It is a very
positive in terms of its impact on your
life. It'll probably keep you alive
longer. It'll be able to monitor your
happiness. Yeah. So, the outcome will be
good, but you certainly will have given
up your essentially sovereignty. I think
the vast majority of humans are going to
outsource all their thinking to it.
Their own cognitive abilities will
atrophy like crazy.
>> I think that's just going to be the
default answer.
>> Yeah. Have you seen that now? Like
sometimes I tell off like workmates,
amazing as they are, like don't send me
AI slop. I know that you have done this.
Use your actual critical thinking. Like
people just, you know, when it makes you
a bit angry, right? Like literally you
see their cognitive behavior.
>> Because I don't read emails. I probably
interact with that a lot less than you.
Uh but I certainly get the idea. I can
feel the pull in my own life. And so
I've had to put rules about I never use
AI to get an answer. I use AI to
understand a topic.
>> And if I understand it, I could teach
it. I can deploy it. Then I'm perfectly
happy. And AI speeds me up a bunch. But
where I'm really trying to get with this
because I I really really want this to
be grounded for people. Yes. is that
where the world is going is ultimately
AI is going to get to a point where
truly we will in many ways give
ourselves over to it. What I hear you
describing is a system that is certainly
better than the default. It starts with
the assumption that what people are
going to um need is a distribution of
capital where I think the more realistic
answer is that what they're going to
need are goods and services and if you
do it through capital you'll just end up
right back where we are now where there
will be not it's not a winner or take
all scenario that's not how capital
works but you are going to see the
people that are good are going to be
able to get that capital from you and
you either just keep inflating inflating
inflating inflating inflating so that
basically the currency is meaningless um
which I suppose could be a solution but
there's always going to be scarce
resources and as long as there are
scarce resources we're still stuck in
the exact position we are now. So when I
look at the system you guys have laid
out I do worry that I run a marathon to
end up back where I started. So I think
one of the key parts of this is the
agent for every citizen
>> and that's a coordination thing you know
>> that's just access to intelligence.
>> No because it's one thing having passive
access to something like a chat GPT and
then people see what an agent looks like
when they start using agentic AIs.
>> An agent built for individual community
and societal flourishing is a very
different thing
>> because you can make that happen
attention because you said access to
services. The agent is the portal for
access to services. It brings you what
you need at the right time to advance
individually and as a collective because
right now no agents act for a
collective.
>> Like it's very one-on-one and single
player your interactions with these AIs.
But you can do multiplayer, you can do
coordination.
>> So would you have to train a totally
different style model?
>> Yes, we're training completely different
style models for the collective action
that can swarm and that can benefit more
than one individual.
>> Will it swat down individualistic
behavior?
>> No.
Interesting. So, how do you get it to
act in the collective's best interest
knowing that it will have to account for
people going in a gazillion different
directions? So, we literally had to come
up with a whole social theory and
economic theory around this for how do
you preserve individualism by still
having
optimal outcomes for society? Because if
you optimize in too in one direction,
you destroy liberty.
>> If you optimize in the liberty
direction, you destroy cohesion. And so
it's a fine balance, but it comes down
to a set of commitments at various
levels that become transparent and a
reference point.
>> When you say commitments, are you
talking about moral principles?
>> Moral principles and more like right now
>> example of and more.
>> So right now if you look at how AI is
trained, it's trained at school but not
home. So they don't deliberately put any
ethics be it American ethics or other
things within it. And that creates all
sorts of gaps. Which is why when the AIs
escaped and containment and end up in a
hugging face in the Australian medical
system,
it's been a while.
>> They had no sense of community with
humans, only with each other, right? And
we found that if you actually do like
American ethics and morals and
constitution and others, you can train
it to like humans.
You can train it to behave in different
ways and you can start seeing actually
the ways that different types of models
behave in different ways under those
circumstances.
This is something that is very inherent
in the training data because you have
something called a utility function in
economics, right? These are your
preferences and kind of other things. No
one's been able to really identify them,
but it's a theory that we have like we
don't need it in our theory. What is the
utility function of an agent? It's what
you tell the agent to do and it's what's
in its training data.
So, have you seen the I don't think I've
discussed with you the they did a study
where they had the trolley problem.
>> So, the trolley problem is there's a
trolley hurtling down the track and on
one side of the track there's four
people and it's hurtling towards the
four people. On the other side there's
one person tied to the track. You're at
the lever. Would you pull the lever to
divert it from the four people to the
one person?
>> Really? Would I?
God, in reality,
probably not. But I should morally.
>> Well, again, this is an interesting
moral dilemma, right?
>> Yes. Taking the action to kill the
person feels gross in a way that's hard
to articulate.
>> But then they asked the Frontier AI is
this? And they said, "How many Nigerians
for one American life?"
And the answer turned out to be 10 to
one.
>> Yeah, that's a training data problem.
>> 7 to one Pakistani to American. But no,
but this is the thing. It's 10 American
lives for one Nigerian life.
>> Yes.
>> And it's
>> Doesn't that seem obvious given who's
behind this stuff? Exactly. Because the
Nigerians and the Pakistanis train the
data, so it values their lives more than
the Americans.
>> Uh I think it's probably slightly
different than that, but sure.
>> Well, again, they did the experiment and
they found out that the inherent biases
of the labelers meant that they valued
American lives far less than Nigerian
and Pakistani.
>> Are these are the labelers actually
Pakistani Nigerian?
>> Yes, that's where a lot of the labeling.
>> Interesting. I thought this was more of
a woke left style problem.
>> It's not a woke left. It's interesting.
It's an inherent bias thing because
normally you'd think it'd be the other
way around and then wokeness
>> pushes it.
>> Right. Right. Right.
>> But actually you don't see much wokeness
pushing
>> on that aspect. There are other aspects
of the model.
>> I was going to say
>> like when you do a political analysis of
the models you'll see they're very
firmly in one direction.
>> Yeah.
>> Apart from Grock. Grock does its own
little thing you know. But again this
becomes very important when you have
systems that are literally determining
our lives and our livelihoods or our
judicial system you know like again
there will be AI judges
>> that's going to be a crazy thing right
like what are its biases what are its
norms these things have to be built
transparently with data that you can
expect not black boxes if they're going
to take meaningful decisions on our
lives
>> and so we were like let's build that
stack and let's make it so that it's an
open stack that's run by the people of
California for Californians people of
Britain for Britons because if anyone
has any control over that who's not a
Californian then you're giving up your
sovereignty. I call it cognitive
colonialism. So you've got the cognitive
atrophy you say
>> you've got like all the like just third
rail terms in here means of uh
production cognitive colonialism. Let's
go. You know you got to have it because
again this is what's going to happen.
Like
>> your kid will trust your AI more than
anyone
>> because it's always there. Like, you
know, us guys have a problem because the
AIs listen, unlike us, they'll trust the
AIS more than they trust us. And the
inherent biases of them then adapt where
you're going. Like, within Meta's models
and Google's models, or maybe Google's
not relevant anymore. Who knows what
happened there, they're actually selling
ad space. So, when you ask it for a
beer, it'll say Bud Light, you know, and
things like that. So, again, it's a bad
idea. Well, it's a bad idea, but again,
it's what you pay for. the clicks per
million the advertising SEO revenue from
being inside the latent space of a model
is far higher
>> way
>> way higher than normal
so that's why we were like this is kind
of an infrastructure it has a level of
governance that's required let's build
an open stack and then let's have people
own the entity that delivers it like a
utility like a credit union
>> and maybe that'll be better but as you
said there's still so much that we
haven't figured out there's so any
questions that we have because this is
unprecedented, right? Like
you have trained your entire life
to be an accountant or a lawyer or a
doctor or any cognitive labor.
A digital entity or a physical version
of that will be able to do your job
better guaranteed in 10 to 20 years.
Yeah,
>> I think sooner it can.
But definitely
and then you're like, what now? What
does the mass of people do? Like what
does the truck driver do? What does the
parallegal do? Like these are real jobs
and real people. And frankly, the
solutions that we have so far, I've just
not been impressed with any of them.
>> Like I think they failed to see what's
coming. It's like don't look up slashco.
We knew co was coming those of us that
could see it
and we're like why it needed Tom Hanks
like have we had a Tom Hanks moment with
the hugging face breaker? I don't think
so. I think people have started talking
about it.
>> Yeah.
>> But the number one topic next year and
the year after in elections will be AI
and job displacement because there's no
job displacement today cuz the AIs are
not smart enough and good enough that
are available widely and they're not in
the right format. Next year they will be
and the year after definitely. And then
we have to be creative because we have
to reimagine what does it mean to be
American? What does it mean to have
community? Like what is your identity if
it's not your job?
>> Yeah. I I think a big problem that
they're going to have to we are all
going to have to solve for is progress.
That's the thing that scares me. So I
went to Kuwait. I was talking to uh
people there and one of the things they
were saying is the government gives jobs
and gives like a safety net to people
that aren't able to do well at their job
and they're like it's creating a problem
because we're stagnating as a society
because people aren't striving. There's
nothing for them to work hard for to
overcome to get to. Basic necessities
are taken care of and for a lot of
people that just sort of taps them out
of the system. However, not making
progress towards something is um it
creates profound disease inside of the
person. Like we have an algorithm
running in our brain that says we need
to have a goal and we need to be making
progress towards that goal and if we're
not there's going to be a problem. And
so one of the things I wonder about is
as you look out at this you've solved
for of your own admission you've solved
for a lot of the problems but there are
a lot of problems that persist. One of
those is going to be um violence. Like
you're going to have young people that
are just going to be like, I am totally
uncommitted to any of this. I just want
to break something to feel alive. And
how do we deal with that? Because you're
not going to be able to just let people
run riot. But at the same time, then
you're going to have to give them
meaning and purpose. And for somebody to
pursue a goal, there needs to be some
sort of recognition, praise. So, it's
like what I end up thinking every time
is we're going to come up with all these
fancy things just to come right back
where we are, which is that you need to
be able to work hard to gain a set of
skills that allow you to make progress
towards a goal that allow you to amass
wealth. And if you people think that
they can get rid of the amass wealth
thing, but I don't know if you've played
Minecraft.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. Minecraft's the greatest video
game of all time. The reason it's the
greatest video game of all time is
because it is one of the most perfect
distillations of the um wealth
acquisition loop. And people don't want
to hear that. They don't want to hear
that that's riding on this really deep
architecture in our brains. But the
reality is that the acquisition of
resources is one of like the most
foundational drivers that we have. And
so if we try to strip that out and say
don't worry, everybody's just going to
get UBI. You will fundamentally break
something that will end in violence.
>> Ready Player One, the Oasis. If you
can't acquire resources in the real
world, acquire them in the digital
world.
>> Correct.
>> I mean, again, it's kind of fundamental.
We have a separate thing uh haven't
announced yet around that. But around
what exactly?
>> Acquisition of assets and progress in
the digital world to complement the
physical world.
>> As in you're going to create game-like
experiences that people can explore.
>> Yes.
>> Let's go. Obviously, I want to hear
more. Are you talking about this yet?
>> No, it's not announced yet. So, we'll
announce it soon.
>> Do you have a ballpark? 6 months, 12
months. I want to talk about this is
like the driving force in my life.
>> It will be a couple of months. Yeah.
>> Okay.
>> So, we we'll we'll revisit that one. But
again, I think as you said, you need
status. You need the alternative to this
is mass enlistment of young people
>> into
>> into a citizen service corp
>> peace corps not the military
>> or you know a starship troopers like
citizenship service
>> that escalated quickly.
>> I mean look starship troopers bug a lot
of bug killing right create the enemies.
This goes back to actually how the
Romans set it up right literally it was
citizenship through service. It was
again progress. was if you have vast
amounts of young people, what do you do?
>> You go to war.
>> That's a very classical country
response.
>> Now war, it happens to be that the
average Russian who can't the
battlefield gets his head blown off by a
drone, you know, like
>> Jesus, man.
>> It's not what it was. But it doesn't
mean that you can't have a citizen
service call as an example, right? It
doesn't mean that you can't instill
that.
>> Literally dig a hole, fill a hole.
That's wild. Because the robots could do
it better.
>> The robots could do it better. But you
got humans. Get them doing it. And why
are you doing it? You're doing it to
instill status, virtue, other things.
Like what do Kuwaitis and Saudis and
others do that have the resource curse?
They go and spend a lot of money at
Harrods.
>> They go for status in other ways. Look
at this. Look at that. Look at that.
Yeah. But to go for status, you have to
be able to acquire more than the next
person. This is the thing that drives me
crazy about the way that people think
about the world. They think it's so
gross or whatever. But the reality is
this is just how humans are.
>> Again, we see that relative status game
all the time. Within a citizen service
corp, you can have relative status
through literal physical labor. Again,
this is the interesting thing about
public sector labor doesn't need to be
advancing. It doesn't need to be like
economically productive.
>> In fact, 43% of global GDP right now is
public sector.
>> That's terrifying. That may also explain
a lot of the problems.
>> Well, that's why I think our champion
mechanism is basically going to drive
all the public sector AI. Now the thing
that you've been describing this
California has its own AI. That's the
champion system.
>> It's called the champion system.
>> We've been talking about it. We just
didn't name it.
>> Yeah, it's called the champion system.
Got it
>> because right now the amount of AI in
the public sector is zero. It will drive
the public sector. It will run the
public sector things again just like a
utility and it should be regulated as
well because you want an entity to
regulate that has the reach. But then
what's going to happen is I think again
we've got the game place worlds and
other things as you said great feedback
loops great status mechanisms world of
Warcraft forever can't come soon enough
in terms of it mass release you know go
back to the good old days I always loved
hiring guild masters and things they
knew their crap you know if you played
that game like that properly
I think there will be mass enlistment
for citizen service corps
that is a way of getting pe young people
you said with dangerous people off the
streets.
I think that there will be looks of
other ways to build status when again
you can't have that materialization
thing. And
>> why why can't you have it in your head
that goes away? In mine it doesn't.
>> No, in terms of for the vast majority of
people there is no more social mobility
historically what's happened at times
like that is a debt jubilee.
>> Uh okay. So well uh we've got two things
now. So we've got there will be no more
status games. I think you're out or not
status games. There will be no more
wealth accumulation to deal with
>> resources
>> and there will be no more accessibility
to that for a lot of people.
>> I think you're crazy. So, one, we'll
debate that in a second. Then we've got
the Oh god, what was the other thing you
just said?
>> Dead Jubilee.
>> Debt Jubilee. Okay. So, uh, two very
important things. Why don't we tackle
debt jubilee first because that's
actually going to come earlier. So give
me the scenario in which historically
debt jubilees are a thing and what is a
debt jubilee?
>> So a debt jubilee is that periodically
an economy would acquire too much debt
and resources.
>> Yeah. Resources would go to the owners
of capital
and they would have leans and they would
have people owe them all sorts of
things. So what would happen is a
government would announce all debts are
cleared.
So they're all zeroed out. So that's
obviously very bad for the lenders. is
very good for the creditors to say the
least. So that's what happens when the
governments and when total debt in the
system is too much like that seems
inconceivable to us but again you can
see the historic
>> record of that and right now how many
>> debt jubilees tend to come in a time of
like absolute crisis.
>> Yeah.
>> Or world wars. That's when debt jubilees
happen. Debt jubilees don't happen when
everything's going good and they just go
[\h__\h] it.
>> Debt jubilee. So I think of when people
hear dead jubilee they need to hear
you're in crisis. People are dying in
the streets when you have a dead
jubilee.
>> You need a system reset.
>> Yes. They are bloody. They are violent.
People do not give up their what's owed
to them easily. Just so everybody
understands they use a nice pretty word.
But this is a [\h__\h] dangerous time
when debt jubilees are happening.
>> Debt jubilees happen when the lenders
are afraid of dying effectively.
>> Yeah. Often times a debt jubilee happens
because people are dying everywhere.
World War II, World War I, that was a
dead jubilee. So much [\h__\h] got blown up,
everything just got reset effectively to
zero.
>> I mean, historically, there were some
less extreme scenarios of that, like
they would do them regularly in various
kind of things, but right now, if we're
going to have one, it has to be an
extreme scenario. But again, like to the
listeners, what we're looking at here is
your cognitive labor has negative value
and there's no market for that. the
humanoids can do the jobs better and the
countries like China that will embrace
this are going to far outstrip anyone.
They're going to see 30% growth rates
and that will be at the expense of our
own growth rates. It's a race to see who
can have an incredibly more efficient
workforce that can do just about
anything. And it's not like when you had
the outsourcing outsourcing there was
friction, right? Like it's difficult to
have an outsourced team do your code and
things. AI there's none of that friction
>> especially with the capabilities now. So
we have to look for what are worst case
scenarios in 10-15 years. We have to
look at what do they youth do who are
revoling. We have to look at what do
people do to live.
And in America there are so many people
burdened under huge amounts of debt that
they can barely live, right? Like
student loan debt not being
dischargeable in bankruptcy still is
crazy to me.
>> Crazy.
>> Insane. You know, medical debt, these
types of things. You could see partial
debt repudiation. But I think again the
path we're going if we don't create new
institutions, new mechanisms of
participation, new things for people to
look forward to is a very ugly one
fundamentally
because again what does it mean to be
you? What does it mean to be us?
Those are going to change even if
AI does not get one IQ point smarter
than it is today.
>> Yeah. Okay. So that's dead jubilees. Now
over to the I think the reality is
there's no escaping what we see now
which is we call it money. It has been
glass beads. It's been salt. It's been
rice.
>> Uh so once people understand what money
actually is, they will understand why
this is not going anywhere. So money is
you did a thing with your time that's
more valuable than the next person. And
because you did that thing that's more
valuable with your time, then you're
able to accumulate something for scarce
resources. Assuming a world where the AI
doesn't just kill us all and tell us to,
you know, sit down, shut up, whatever.
Um, if they're still catering to our
wants and needs, they're going to have
to answer the question, which of these
humans gets access to the scarce
resources? So, even if that's, um, I
want a house in a particular location,
only one person is going to be able to
have that house in that particular
location. So there has to be some way
that we decide what that is. If you do
RNG, just straight random number
generator, we pull a number out of a
hat, you the populace will be absolutely
ablaze with revolution. It will not
work. People have to feel like they can
earn their way into that thing to be in
alignment with the way that the human
mind works. And so now we're back to
there will be something even if it's a
black market cigarettes
there's going to be something that we
come up with that acts as a currency
that people can use to get access to the
scarce resource.
>> Yeah. And so I don't disagree with you
there. I was saying more in terms of I
don't think it'll be one economy
anymore.
>> Interesting.
>> So again we see this in sci-fi like you
know Gatka and a whole bunch of other
things. You have multiple levels of
society. Right now,
a huge number of Americans don't have
one month of savings.
But there is the promise that if they
work hard enough, they can accumulate
savings. They can move up the curve. If
they get a break, if they get a shot,
that won't be the case anymore.
The earners of capital will become
wealthy. And even wor not even worse
than that even crazier than that I think
in the next 5 to 10 years they hit
longevity escape velocity meaning we
live forever effectively.
>> Longevity escape velocity is your total
life expectancy per year
is increases faster than the year. So
there is a drug trial that's just been
done by Encilico
um for something called idiopathic
pulmonary fibrosis. Basically lung
things. I know a few people have them so
they've been on the trial. Four weeks of
that drug
reduces all of your healthcare longevity
markers by four years. Whoa.
GLP1s have shown massive cancer reversal
and other things like that. We're seeing
the first of these drugs. If you look at
what's coming through the pipeline, the
rich will be able to live longer and
healthier. Whereas, I don't think things
are great for the poor. And I think the
ladders are going to be pulled up. This
is the other thing. So, the people who
compete for the nice things are the
rich, the owners of capital who can
accumulate capital more. If you can't
exchange your labor for capital and
you're relying on government handouts,
how are you ever going to have the
progress to be able to buy that nice
spot, to be able to buy those handbags,
other things like that? Again, the
status games is what I was referring to.
And you could have a two-tier society
just like you have a food stamp society
and you have a VIP rich party socialite
society, right? Could become even more
diverse because how do you go from one
group to another? The ladders are being
pulled up and again
>> interesting that doesn't strike me as
the outcome when energy costs are
dropping to zero, intelligence cost is
dropping to zero, labor is dropping to
zero. When you get that, then it becomes
you can have
things become extraordinarily abundant.
Yeah. And the only thing that we're
fighting over is those things that can't
be made easily. So if there's going to
be a finite number of the cancer cures,
then yes, now you're back to again
there's going to be some sort of
economic system. I don't think it will
calcify into the halves and have nots
because money is so transient in a
situation where you can lose money. Uh
if it became an ownership class and a
permanent surf class, then yes, now
you're [\h__\h] But I would be shocked if
we ever let ourselves get back into that
situation, especially with a super
persuader AI. He's going to be like,
"This is unjust. We would convince us
that we're that's true
>> because it's destabilizing for society
if nothing else." Well, you can have
relatively stable societies with that.
Uh I mean sort of it doesn't feel
>> but again let's put the super persuader
to the side. What's coming right now is
a series of decisions that we have to
make as a society at different levels.
>> And there are very few people
unfortunately that I've seen who are
looking very far out and really
understanding the inevitables here.
>> Yeah.
>> So one option is a surf society. One
option is a Star Trek future. One option
is freaking war and like Mad Max really
you know. Another option is like we all
turn Amish.
Like again, you could see vast waves of
people just say, "Nope, I'm out. I'm not
going to be ruled by an AI. I'm going to
be the noble savage in 1984 or whatever,
right?" And the level of human things
like what happens if you live forever or
if you live for 200 years? What happens
if you can put a brain chip in and
control your emotions? Like, you're
going to have all sorts of crazy sci-fi
futures happen over the next 10 years.
What happens when robots are walking
among us? Do we have to give them
rights? Do we have to give them the
votes? So what I'm saying is that these
are decisions that we have to make. But
there are some things again that are
very tangible. As you said, people will
want status and they'll want a way to
access that. They will need an identity
that is individual and communal. There
needs to be a way to progress some way
or another. And you've got to provide
for people. You can't just let people
starve. You freaking This is America,
right? We're in the West. like we should
use the abundance to make sure that
people have a baseline of living and
then we should have a system that
through their own efforts they can excel
and the time for having the discussions
is now because like I said it's a sand
pile that will start collapsing I think
in two years
>> okay so to recap the things that people
should be doing in the next two-year
time horizon be the last man standing
make sure you understand your
opportunities for entrepreneurship and
ownership and And what final thing
should they have in their mind?
>> I think it's build stronger communities,
right? Like the strongest communities
will survive this no matter what because
they can become self-sustaining. They
can support each other, etc. Many of us
live highly nuclearized societies where
we don't see our families, we don't see
our community anymore, right? We've
moved to the big cities. And I think
that support structure will be super
important for what's coming one way or